Guide to the Violet Oakley Papers, 1921-1982
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Violet Oakley Papers
1921-1982
Oakley, Violet, 1874-1961
0.2 cubic feet (1 box, 1 OV folder)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Correspondence, exhibition and publication programs, and other printed materials related to the work of American artist Violet Oakley, particularly the large-scale triptych she painted for the Vassar College Alumnae House in 1924, The Great Wonder: A Vision of the Apocalypse.
Biographical Note
Violet Oakley (1874-1961) was an American artist. Born on June 10, 1874 in Bergen Heights, New Jersey to Arthur Edmund Oakley and Cornelia Swain, Oakley grew up in a family of artists. Between 1892 and 1896, she studied at the Art Students League of New York, in England and France under artists including Raphael Collin, at the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, and at the Dexel Institute. Oakley was commissioned by Louise Lawrence Meigs (VC 1891) to create the triptych mural The Great Wonder: A Vision of the Apocalypse for the opening of the Vassar College Alumnae House in 1924. Oakley created the triptych as a memorial to her sister, Hester Caldwell (Oakley) Ward (VC 1891), who died of typhoid fever in 1905.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of correspondence, exhibition and publication programs, and other printed materials related to the work of American artist Violet Oakley, particularly the large-scale triptych she painted for the Vassar College Alumnae House in 1924, The Great Wonder: A Vision of the Apocalypse.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Violet Oakley papers, 1841-1981. Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution.
Works by Violet Oakley, Frances Lehman Loeb Art Center, Vassar College.
Subject Headings
Organizations:
Vassar College--Alumni and alumnae
Subjects:
Illumination of books and manuscripts
Document Types:
Correspondence; Printed ephemera; Prints (visual works)
VCL Categories:
Art and Artists; Vassar College
Encoding Information
Encoded by Emma Gronbeck, January 2024.
Acquisition Information
Gift of various donors.
Container List
- Christmas card, 1925; [1 item] (Folder 1)
- Clipping: "The Great Wonder," Vassar Quarterly, 1924 Nov; [1 letter] (Folder 2)
- Correspondence: Emerson, Edith to Borden, Fanny, 1941 May 20; [3 letters] (Folder 3)
- Correspondence: Emerson, Edith to Underhill, Adelaide, 1924-1926; [2 letters] (Folder 4)
- Correspondence: Oakley, Violet to Borden, Fanny, 1939-1940; [16 letters] (Folder 5)
- Correspondence: Oakley, Violet to and from Underhill, Adelaide, 1921-1932; [3 items] (Folder 6)
- Cogslea Academy of Arts and Letters, pamphlets, 1937-1941; [6 items] (Folder 7)
- Exhibition programs and ephemera, 1923-1942; [1 item] (Folder 8)
- Exhibitions: "Catalogue of Studies and Drawings for Mural Decorations," program, 1923 Jun; [3 items] (Folder 9)
- Exhibitions: "The Founding of the Statue of Liberty Spiritual," program and ephemera, circa 1922; [3 items] (Folder 10)
- Memo: "Dimensions of V. Oakley Triptych,", 1979 May 11; [4 copies] (Folder 11)
- Oakley, Violet, "The Great Wonder," program, 1924; [4 copies] (Folder 12)
- Oakley, Violet, "The Great Wonder," triptych print, undated; [5 items] (Multiple Collections Box 2 (Oversize))
- Oakley, Violet, The Holy Experiment, ephemera, circa 1922; [5 items] (Folder 13)
- Oakley, Violet, "La Presence Divine a la Societe des Nations [Divine Presence at the League of Nations]," publication, 1937; [1 item] (Folder 14)
- Philadelphia Museum of Art, Bulletin, "Violet Oakley,", 1979 Jun; [photocopy] (Folder 15)
- Violet Oakley Memorial Foundation gift to Vassar College Art Gallery, inventory, 1982; [1 item] (Folder 16)